《斯巴达克斯：血与沙》
《精致》
我们经历过噩运
We have seen misfortune.
尝过失败的痛苦
Felt the sting of defeat.
知道手中没钱 腹内空空的感觉
The humility of vacant purse and empty stomach.
有人以为Batiatus家族
Some believed the House of Batiatus
不能重振声威
would never reclaim its former glory.
以为我们将从人们的记忆中淡出 被历史抹除
That we would fade from memory, forsaken by history.
但今天 我们证实了他们的错误
But we have proved them wrong.
耶!
Yeah!
我们证明了Batiatus之名
We have proved the name Batiatus
将万古长青
will live long after we have gone to dust and bone.
万岁!
Yeah!
让我们自豪地 矗立在雨神面前!
So stand proud before the Bringer of Rain!
屠灭死亡之影的勇士!
The Slayer of the Shadow of Death!
卡普亚的新战神!
The new champion of Capua!
斯巴达克斯!
Spartacus!
耶!
Yeah!
斯巴达克斯! 斯巴达克斯!
Spartacus! Spartacus!
这位勇士 他的胜利 空前绝后!
A Titan, his victory eclipsing all others!
解了我们的饥渴!
Quenching our thirst!
达成了我们的希望和梦想!
Fulfilling our hopes and dreams!
他成为传奇的一刻 万众瞩目!
Behold the man, as he becomes legend!
耶!
Yeah!
这只是个开始!
This is only the beginning!
有你在 大业得成是迟早的事!
I will build an empire of blood and glory upon your name!
打败Theokoles 可不是他一个人的功劳
He did not stand against Theokoles on his own.
还有Crixus
Crixus is not forgotten.
如果他能活下来 自然有他一席
He will always have position, if he survives.
但目前 斯巴达克斯正当红
But Spartacus is the name on the crowd's tongue.
我期待看到你
And I would see it spoken
再造佳绩
with ever increasing amazement.
我打败了一个不败的传说
I defeated a man who could not be defeated.
他们还想我做什么?
What more could they expect of me?
做一切能做之事!
Everything!
民众的欲望是无底洞
Their appetite is a great beast.
需要不断尝鲜
It must constantly be fed with new delights.
我们就从改变你的角斗风格开始
We'll start by changing your fighting style.
像Theokoles一样 手执双剑
Two swords, as Theokoles fought with.
民众对你的喜爱之情
We'll see the crowds pleasure double
也会比Theokoles多一倍!
with their new hero twice as deadly!
再穿件与传奇人物相称的 新战袍!
And new armor, worthy of a legend!
让男人自惭形秽!
Men will be made to feel smaller by it!
让女人春心荡漾
Women will moisten at the very sight.
啊 我忘了
Ah, but I forget.
他似乎对女人荡漾的春心不感兴趣 对吗?
He has no hard purpose for just any wet thigh, does he?
我可不管他对什么感兴趣
He and his purpose are not my concern.
幸好天神眷顾
Fortunately the gods feel otherwise.
他们对他青眼有加 不惜普降甘霖来盛加赞扬...
They shower him with more than rain and accolades...
他们庇佑他
They bless him with news to lift the heart
威名远播
higher than the clouds.
Sura呢?
Sura?
找到了!
Found!
在叙利亚的某个地方
In the dark corners of Syria.
她... 在哪?
Where... where is she?
她还好么?
Is she well?
安然无恙!
Peace!
你别急 听我说!
All will be revealed when a mouth closes!
那个叙利亚人Glaber 又把她卖给了一个商人
The Syrian Glaber spoke of sold her to a merchant,
当他的情妇
the sea his mistress.
他最近在那不勒斯靠过岸
He has recently docked on the shores of Neapolis.
在罗马?
On Roman soil?
你的妻子和奴隶在一起
Your wife among the slaves.
不出意外 2天就能赶到
Two days ride from where you stand, barring incident.
我们何时动身?
When do we leave?
这样做好吗?
Is it wise to allow such a thing?
我的人已快马加鞭 你大可放心
My man already spurs his horse, rest at ease.
我们说话这会儿 她已经离我们越来越近了
She moves ever closer even as we speak.
你是个值得尊敬的人
You are an honorable man.
我永世感激你
And will forever bear my gratitude.
我也一样
As you bear mine.
和你妻子团聚
Being reunited with your wife
只是第一个奖赏而已
is but the first of many rewards.
谢谢你 主人
Dominus.
你瞒着我
Secrets.
半点口风都没泄
Secrets upon secrets.
我也是刚知道她被找到了
The news of her discovery only just reached me.
Ovidius一家怎么了?
And what of good Ovidius and his family?
你为什么背着我 把他们都杀了?
Why did you keep plans towards their slaughter from me?
只为了减少点债务么
And all to clear a few debts.
跟债务无关 是为了报仇
It had nothing to do with debt, except one of blood.
他是幕后凶手 意图在竞技赌场杀掉我
His was the hand behind attempt on my life in the pits.
Ovidius做的?
Ovidius?
是Solonius授意的
Moved to purpose by Solonius.
我瞒着你 不是怕你知道 而是出于爱
I keep from you not out of secrecy, but from love.
我不想让你为这些事担心
I would not have you stained by such things.
我们现在是人们交相传唱的对象
We are the toast of the fucking city.
让我们尽情享受吧
Let us pause and enjoy it.
给你住的单间
Yours alone.
没有别人了?
Not to be shared?
这是你值得的
Your achievement in earning it profound.
没你的指导 不可能成功
Made possible by your instruction.
我只帮你赢得了上场机会而已
My actions only set you to the task.
但杀掉Theokoles
By depriving Theokoles of his life,
你替我完成了未尽之战
you put end to a battle left unfinished by my sword.
也结束了我羞耻的历史
An end to my shame.
多亏你 我才有活着见到妻子的机会
I live to see my wife again, because of you.
这个恩情我永世铭记
A debt not soon forgotten.
我们之间不谈恩情
There is no balance between us.
只要记得为荣誉而战
Only the promise of future glory.
可以点蜡烛吗?
Are candles permitted?
Sura总喜欢点着蜡烛
Sura was always fond of them.
你误会了
You misunderstand.
只有你能住在这里
This cell is for you alone.
妻子不能和我们住在一起
Wives are not permitted to live among us.
那她住哪儿?
Then where will she stay?
房子里
In the villa.
保证生命安全 但作为回报
Kept safe and well in return
要服侍好主人
for good service to the Domina.
作为奴隶来服侍
As a slave.
就像我们一样
As are we all.
但你的地位升得太快
But you rise quickly,
和以往我所知道的任何一个人 都不同
unlike any other I've ever witnessed.
继续保持这势头 你就能获得自由了
Continue your ascent, and you will gain freedom.
你们俩都能自由
For both of you.
Ashur啊
Ashur.
Barca啊!
Barca!
我就是来找你的
I was this very moment coming to have words.
得了吧
Keep them.
拿钱来
I would have coin instead.
Theokoles会败 真是太让人吃惊了
It is no small marvel, the fall of Theokoles.
这么意外的结果 这么悬殊的赔率
Your wager in the favor of the unexpected outcome,
你下的注...
the size of the odds...
要付清这么一大笔钱
It's not a simple matter,
可不是件容易的事 对吧?
to cover a win of such margin, eh?
怎么搞钱 我才不管
I give no shit for margins.
去讨 去偷 或杀人越货 要搞钱容易得很
Beg, steal, or kill to cover what is owed.
否则你就等着双腿残废吧
Or you will have two worthless legs.
中间那条也跟着废了
And nothing in between to prop yourself up.
我找过瘸子了
I've had exchange with the cripple.
他给钱了?
He pays what is owed?
钱很快就能到手了
Soon the coin will be in hand.
足以让我们换回自由之身
Enough to buy our freedom.
自由 呃... 这个词对我来说 还真陌生
Freedom, err... the word is foreign to the tongue.
很快就不陌生了
It will learn to savor the taste.
鸟儿们该怎么办?
What of the birds?
它们也会像我们一样 重获自由的
They will fly this place as we do.
我看看都有什么衣服可穿 准备一下为好
I will see what clothes we have packed and ready.
我们要去往何方 要去多远的地方?
Which direction shall we travel and how far?
能走多远 是多远
As far as desire wills our feet.
这件斗篷
This cloak.
是你走的时候 穿在身上的
It was the one you wore when you left.
就是Ovidius被杀的那个晚上
When good Ovidius was murdered.
他罪有应得
There was nothing good about him.
那么 是你杀了他?
Then it was you who killed him?
还有他所有的奴隶?
All his slaves?
以及他的家人...
His family...
我听令行事而已
My hands did what they were commanded.
Ovidius的儿子
What of the young boy.
才那么小啊
Ovidius' son.
你也杀了他么?
Did they take his life too?
我听令行事
Such were my orders.
但你知道
But you know of my affection
我对小东西的感情
for delicate things.
那小孩没死
The boy was spared,
他被送去了外地
and set to wander far from the deed.
等找到他的时候 我们早就是自由身了
By the time he is discovered, we will be free.
那你的双手呢?
And your hands?
从此不再沾染鲜血
Clean forever more.
只听你的吩咐...
And yours to command...
斯巴达克斯的胜利 让整座城市为之沸腾!
Spartacus' victory ignites the imagination of the city!
平民百姓
Orders for my men
家家户户
flood in from every family with half a name
都为我的手下而倾倒!
and a little coin!
繁荣兴盛 触手可及!
Prosperity beyond measure is within our reach!
那些想要你命的人 也近在咫尺了
As are those who would have you dead.
我会让Solonius付出代价的
I will see Solonius pay for the grievance.
但这些急不来
But these things are not be hurried.
当我用绳子绞紧他脖子的时候
I would savor every drop of sweat from his brow
我会尽情享受他流出的每一滴血
as my noose tightens upon his neck.
真希望这一刻快点到来
I would prefer it tighten quickly.
呃 瓜熟自会蒂落
Eh, everything to its season.
谈点眼前的事吧
Turning towards more pressing matters.
真的要让色雷斯人 夫妻团圆吗?
Reuniting the Thracian with his wife?
我要说的 不是这个
Not the matter I was referring to.
和那女奴玩一把 我想看
Have the girl's ass a bit and I'll watch.
我会让你大饱眼福的...
And I would give pleasure to your eyes...
色雷斯人的老婆 总让我放心不下
The Thracian woman concerns me.
找到她的那个承诺
The promise of finding her
是唯一能牵制他的事
was the only thing that kept him in check.
万一她的出现 让他重新变得桀骜不驯
What if her presence reverts him to his Thracian ways,
那该怎么办?
and thoughts of defiance?
不会的
It will not.
你为何如此肯定?
How can you be so sure?
你没看到他眼中的感激之泪吗?
Did you see the tears of gratitude in his eyes?
感激不及忠诚
Gratitude falls short of loyalty.
他不是Crixus那样的人
He's not the man Crixus is.
Crixus也不是他这样的人
And Crixus is not the man he was,
永远也不会是
and may never be again.
斯巴达克斯将和妻子团圆
Spartacus will be reunited with his wife.
到那时...
And in the act...
我会让他离不开我们 和这个训练场...
I will bind him to us and this ludus...
除非天神下令...
Until god comes to claim us all...
你要怎么救我们?
How will you save us?
我是说这场雨
From the rain.
你的胜利让天降甘霖
Your victory splits the skies.
我们淹死前 你又怎么让雨停下来?
How will you close them before we all drown?
你还真跟他们一样傻?
You believe the rest of the fools, then?
以为我受天神庇佑?
That I am blessed by the gods?
你身上 总有奇迹发生
Miracles do take habit of shooting out of your ass.
我听到些更匪夷所思的事
I've heard whispers of yet more divine providence.
关于Sura
Sura.
是真的吗?
Is it true?
她正从那不勒斯 赶回到我的怀抱
She speeds to my arms from Neapolis.
但你仍不敢置信
And still you doubt the god's favor you.
如果天神
If what Sura has been forced to endure
真要Sura受什么罪
is parcel of their favor,
我宁愿他们冲着我来
I would rather they turn their back on me.
如果世上真有天神的话
If they exist at all.
她来了
She comes.
这才是最重要的
That is all that matters now.
你曾经以自由之身 住在这里
You once lived free in these lands.
她会从哪边来?
From which way does she travel?
那不勒斯港在那个方向
The port in Neapolis lies in that direction.
有朝东的路 可以上山吗?
Are there roads to the mountains that lead east?
有几条
Several.
哪几条最人迹罕至?
Which ones are the most sparsely traveled?
拿这么怪的问题 来转换话题
An odd question, removed from the subject.
转换得不算成功
Not so far astray.
嗯 的确有些路人迹罕至
Yes, some are sparsely traveled.
但如果有人起疑的话 这些路
But not to the point of the new champion of fucking Capua
尚不足以令卡普亚的新战神 掩藏踪迹
going unnoticed, if overcome by questionable thoughts.
你觉得 还要多久
How long do you think before Batiatus
Batiatus才能让我赎回自由?
would allow me to buy our freedom?
她要受多少年的折磨?
How many years will she be condemned to bow and scrape?
要不干脆一死了之?
Death the alternative?
你想逃出墙外
You move to escape beyond these walls,
一定是这个下场
and that is surely what you'll find.
难道以前没有先例吗?
Has no one ever attempted such a thing?
活下来?
And lived?
没有
No.
这是不可能的事
It is a thing born of the impossible.
之前也说Theokoles不可战胜
The same was said of defeating Theokoles.
你已经有计划了?
You have a plan, then?
刚刚成型...
One begins to take shape...
这就是你的计划?
That's your plan?
我怕它会胎死腹中
I fear it malformed.
怎么会?
In what way?
首先是武器
Weapons, to begin.
这个在训练场多得是
In large supply at a ludus.
呃 但锁着呢 你又没钥匙
Ah, but kept by lock and key.
难道你以为天神会让钥匙 跟着雨一起
Or do you believe the gods will drop one from the sky
落下来?
along with the rain?
我相信天无绝人之路
I believe in opportunity.
我也有能力拿到
And the power of reason to seize upon it.
想得真美
Fair enough.
看你怎么去"拿"武器
Say you somehow "reason" up a weapon.
马呢?
What of a horse?
没有马 你连山的边儿 都碰不到
You'll never reach the mountains without one.
由主人提供
Dominus provides one.
Sura会坐马车回来...
Sura arrives by cart...
好吧 这无关紧要
Well it won't matter.
武器 马 这些都是小问题
Weapons, horses, they're the least of your concerns.
那还有什么大问题?
And the greatest?
能把你拦下来的人...
The one man that could stop you...
我没考虑过他
I had not considered him.
你欠考虑的事 多了去了
You have not considered many things.
就此打住吧 拜托
Take pause, I beg of you.
不行
No.
我们必须要争得自由
We will have our freedom.
我要拥她入怀
I will take her in my arms,
听她呢喃我的名字
and hear her speak my name.
我的名字
My name.
不是罗马人硬加到我头上的那个
Not the one the Romans branded me with.
我无能为力
I cannot help you in this.
我也不会要你帮忙
I would not ask it.
如果不是为了我的家人...
If it weren't for my own family...
别管我
Give it no thought.
我要怎样 才能让你悬崖勒马?
Is there nothing I can say to turn you from this path?
怎样都不能
Nothing.
那愿上天保佑你吧
Then may the gods you don't believe in favor you.
神勇无比呢 对吧?
A fine figure, is he not?
简直是天神下凡
A god among men.
我从没见过这么威武的战袍
I've never beheld such magnificent armor.
如果您允许的话
If you grant permission,
我想穿着它 迎接我妻子的归来
I would wear it upon my wife's return.
想让她一见难忘?
A move to impress?
她会为她所看到的 惊叹不已
She will marvel at the sight.
男为悦己者所容
A man must always appear his best in the eyes of love.
你穿着它吧
You may wear it.
当你张开双臂迎接她的时候
And I will even stand by your side
我也会站在你身边
while you welcome her with your open arms.
还有 剑...
The swords, however...
我还要它们干嘛?
What need would I have of them?
打扰一下 行吗?!
Can it be?!
来看看我们的传奇人物?!
The legend himself among us?!
Calavius行政官!
Magistrate Calavius!
见到您 我真高兴
Good fortune to see you.
不 是我很高兴才对!
No, the good fortune is mine!
我儿子Numerius一直念念不忘
My son Numerius cannot cease his talk
斯巴达克斯 和他打败Theokoles的那一仗
of Spartacus and his victory over Theokoles.
为了向你的人表示敬意
He demanded a trip to market to obtain something
他还去市场上 买了点色雷斯的东西
of Thrace in your man's honor.
给他瞧瞧
Show him.
商人说 这是勇士之剑
The merchant said it was a warrior's weapon.
它的确是
As well it is.
看到这些标记吗?
See these marks?
是色雷斯人刻在刀柄上的
Thracians notch their hilts.
每杀一人 刻一道
One for every kill.
杀了Theokoles后 你在剑上刻了多少道?
How many made to yours after slaying Theokoles?
至少能以一抵十了吧!
He must have been worth ten at least!
如果我能有你一半的能力...
If I could wield a sword half as well you...
到我主人的训练场来
Join us at my master's ludus
我会把干掉死亡之影的经验
and I will teach you the blow
都教给你
that brought death to the Shadow.
多棒的主意啊!
A splendid notion!
父亲?
Father?
下午晚点就过去吧
Perhaps a visit later this afternoon.
何必让小伙子忍到那时候?
Why make the boy suffer with anticipation?
现在就来吧
Join us presently.
这种快活的事儿 还是先放放
Joy must be delayed in favor of sorrow.
我还要去处理我堂弟被害的事
I attend to matters relating my cousin's murder.
善良的Ovidius
Good Ovidius.
一想到这 就让人心就痛
The heart constricts at the thought.
但我现在满腔都是复仇之心
But swells with promise of vengeance.
Numerius! 跟我走!
Numerius! Come!
稍后 我们再来赴你的盛情邀请
Your generous hospitality will be appreciated shortly.
邀请行政官的儿子来训练场?
An invitation to school the Magistrate's son?
若是我冒失了 那真抱歉
Apologies, if I offered out of turn.
去你的抱歉!
Fuck apologies!
真是个鬼点子 我怎么就没想到!
Shrewd maneuvering, if ever I saw it!
否则我早给你弄个罗马人来了!
I'll make a Roman of you yet!
他不能睁开眼吗?
Should his eyes not be open?
情绪要保持镇定 才能愈合伤痛
Calm is needed to heal the wound.
我用药让他得以安睡
I keep him at rest with herb.
他会好吗?
He will recover?
我尽力了
I've done what I can.
听天命吧
It rests in the hands of the gods.
不
No.
他的命在你掌握之中
His life now rests in your hands.
如果他死了
And I will see them parted
我要你碎尸万段
from your fucking body if he dies.
看到大家对你的喜爱吗?
See how they all look at you?
我父亲有很多杰出的角斗士
My father had many champions,
但没一个能胜过斯巴达克斯!
but none to rival the great Spartacus!
你几乎能听到金币落入口袋的响声了
You can almost smell the coins dropping into our purse.
如果有钱的话 抵消完Sura的交通费
If I may, what remains of my own coin,
我还有多少剩?
after Sura's transport?
你想给你老婆买点什么吗?
You wish to buy something for your wife?
这里的东西都是卖给罗马人的
This market is for proper Romans,
不适合奴隶
it would not suit a slave.
我不是为了自己 而是为其他角斗士
I ask not for me, but for the men.
我想弄些红酒和女人 来共庆我的胜利
Wine and women, in celebration of my victory.
这么做 能让人心悦臣服
A noble gesture, to be much appreciated.
你花点儿钱
You pay with your own coin,
让他们开心开心 对我也有好处
yet their happiness is a benefit to me.
很好 就这么办吧
Very well, let it be done.
呃 Marcellus能搞到这些
Ah, Marcellus is of sound choice towards the vice.
需要我去找他吗?
Shall I make arrangement?
别花得太多
See that there is ample remainder.
遵命 主人
Dominus.
走 为行政官的到来做准备去吧
Come, let us prepare for the Magistrate's arrival.
又来恐吓我?
More threats then, is it?
不是
No.
给你钱 用来买红酒和女人
Coin, to the purpose of wine and whores.
要多得足够满足我主人的手下
Enough to wet tongue and cock for my master's men.
我欠了角斗士Barca很多钱
And a large matter of debt to the gladiator Barca,
我想请你帮我...
that I would ask assistance with...
我打不过来
I have no hand for this.
你的腰带 和那装饰品
Your belt and adornments.
会阻碍你发力
They hinder your purpose.
你的战袍如此沉重 但你却能步履轻盈
Your armor is heavy and yet you move swiftly.
火候到了 你也可以
In time, so will you.
但是真正的勇士 只需要一把剑
But a true warrior needs only a sword
去挑战命运
to cleave his fate.
我明白了
I see your meaning.
我们再来一次
Let us go again.
扮作Theokoles 我来呼风唤雨...
Play Theokoles, and I will attempt to bring the rains...
很抱歉 我们来晚了
Apologies for our late arrival.
我在堂弟那儿的调查进展 真是...
My inquiry at my cousin's villa was...
一团糟
overwhelming.
你打算怎么办?
How did you fare?
只希望他一路走好了
As expected when walking on dead relatives.
贵公子真是学剑奇才
Your son is a quick study with the sword.
简直是为成为角斗士而生的
Born of a fascination with gladiators.
他15岁生日快到了
His fifteenth birthday approaches,
听他说 想在生日会上
my ears are assaulted with request for a pair
看看角斗士表演
to show demonstration at his party.
我本来还指望雇Solonius的人
I had thought to engage Solonius' men,
但自从你的人打败了Theokoles后
but his wares have fallen out of fashion
他的人显然已不值一提了
since your victory over Theokoles.
看来贵公子喜欢时下强者
It seems your son has a taste for what is in favor.
我希望他能满意
And I would see him well fed.
来吧 我们谈谈出场费
Come. Let us negotiate a price for the meal.
主人 打扰一下
Begging pardon, Dominus.
我有封信函 要呈给Calavius行政官
I bring word of great import to Magistrate Calavius.
伟人
An important man,
总不忘时刻关注民情!
seldom out of reach of public matters!
啊 这消息与公众无关
Ah, this message strikes more personal.
Ovidius的儿子还活着!
Ovidius' boy yet lives!
太不可思议了
Well this is fantastic.
这怎么可能?
How can it be?
上天庇佑
By Jupiter's blessing.
有人在卡普亚以北稍远的地方 发现了他
He was discovered miles north of Capua,
他当时正在路边游荡!
wandering the road!
他说什么了?
What of his words?
说那天的现场惨状了吗?
Does he describe the horrors?
关于他怎么活下来的细节
How he came to survive.
目前还不清楚
Details not yet clear.
Numerius 我们走!
Numerius, come!
别忘了你的东西
Do not forget your things.
感谢指教
Gratitude for the lesson.
真是无上荣幸
It was an honor.
Numerius啊!
Numerius!
那个孩子怎么还活着?
How can the boy still be alive?
不应该的啊
He could not.
你亲眼看他死的?
Your eyes held his death?
没有
No.
我交给Barca去处理了
I left the deed in Barca's hands.
我们的命 如今也攥在他手上
And our lives as well.
我们现在怎么办?
What are we going to do?
靠 动脑子想啊!
Fuck. Think!
抱歉打扰
Pardon the intrusion.
庆祝会的东西到了
Provision for the celebration arrive.
去他的庆祝会!
Cunt with celebration!
迦太基混蛋耍得我们团团转
We are betrayed by the beast of fucking Carthage
你却跑过来说酒和女人!
and you bray about wine and whores!
Barca吗?
Barca?
是的
Yeah.
他一向很忠诚的
The man has always been loyal.
忘恩负义的家伙
As a snake to the breast.
Ovidius的儿子还活着
The son of Ovidius lives.
太不幸了
Unfortunate news.
那孩子看到你的脸了吗?
Would the boy know your face?
没有 我在暗处
No I was in shadow.
但Barca暴露在明处
But Barca was clearly revealed.
真不敢相信 Barca会背叛你
I cannot believe Barca would betray you.
我也没想到...
And yet...
你要能想到办法 就赶快说出来
If you have knowledge, bring it to light.
Barca赌Theokoles会输
Barca placed a wager against Theokoles,
赚了一大笔
winning sizeable coin.
我无意中听到 他跟Pietros说
I overheard him whisper to Pietros
打算用这些钱帮他们自己赎身
intentions to buy their freedom with it.
Barca从没提过 有离开这儿的想法呀
Barca has never mentioned desire to leave these walls.
他想在事实败露前离开
He seeks to fly before discovery.
如果那孩子看到他的脸
If the child is allowed to look upon his face,
就会被认出来 他是你的人
he will be known as your man.
集合守卫 去带Barca回来
Gather proper guard and return with Barca.
我要听听从他嘴里 说出来的事实
I would hear truth spilled from his mouth.
当一个人压力很大的时候 谎言会随口而出
When a man is pressed, lies flow with greater ease.
做掉他 就完事了
End him and be done with it.
在我没亲眼看到
Not before I look into his eyes,
他是否背叛我之前 不能杀
and see if treachery lurks there.
没准儿还有其他办法
Perhaps there is another path to illumination.
经验丰富的人 总是很敏感...
One traveled by more delicate sensibilities...
明天宿醉醒来 角斗士们反应会比较迟缓
Tomorrow the men will be slow from drink.
一半的守卫也和他们一样
And half the guards with them.
其中只有一个没有享受
There is one that does not partake
你施予的乐趣...
in your joyous offerings...
一个原则性很强 不会轻易分心的人
A man of higher principle, not so easily distracted.
Crixus怎样了?
How does Crixus fare?
还在梦乡里
Adrift in the land of dreams.
医师还在照料他呢 希望能康复
Kept there yet by the Medicus, in hope of recovery.
我会前往致敬
I would pay my respects.
你想淹死我啊!
You drown me!
这么多酒...
In more than just wine...
Pietros啊
Pietros.
主人召见你
You are summoned.
你在干嘛?
What are you doing?
来和我兄弟分享胜利的喜悦!
I come to share drink with my partner in victory!
表达下你的敬意就走吧 他需要休息
Well, pay your respects and be gone, he needs rest.
别再让他喝了
And keep that fucking wine from his lips.
兄弟 没有你的话
Without you, brother,
洒落在竞技场的就不是雨
my blood would have fallen in the arena
而是我的血了!
instead of the rain!
愿神灵永远以Crixus为荣 战无不胜的高卢人!
May the gods forever honor Crixus, the Undefeated Gaul!
原谅我带来的伤痛
And forgive the pain I cause.
让开!
Move aside!
他的伤口又裂开了
His wound has reopened.
把褐色的罐子拿过来!
The brown jar!
快!
Quickly!
这能治愈他吗?
Will this heal him?
不能
No.
但能让他镇定下来睡着 这样我就能缝合伤口了
But it will calm him to sleep so that I may seal the wound.
他会没事吧?
Will he be all right?
快滚出去!
Get the fuck out!
我已经喝太多了...
I've had too much wine already...
很值得尝尝啊
None of worth.
这是费乐年葡萄酒
This is Falernian,
我们从没从此痛饮过
none of that swill flowing below us.
呃 确实太爽了
Um, it truly tastes of the gods.
快赶上神仙的生活了
And brings us closer to them.
Barca怎样了?
How fares Barca?
精神不错 和其他所有人一样
In fine spirits, as are all the men.
你值得信任吗?
Is your confidence to be trusted?
当然 主人
Yes, of course Dominus.
几天前
Several days ago,
我被迫去收拾那个
I was forced to take retribution against Ovidius,
粮商Ovidius
the grain merchant.
他试图在地下赌场取我的性命
He had made attempt on my life in the pits.
他是个威胁 不可信
The man was a danger and not to be trusted,
所以要好好教训下他
he had to be handled accordingly.
你明白吗?
You understand?
现在到处都是留言
Now rumors abounds that more than Ovidius
说不止Ovidius被杀了
gave up their lives.
他全家人 都被屠杀了
His entire family, slain.
里面甚至还有个小孩
There was even a child.
其他人 我可以不在意
The rest I can put from mind.
但对那个男孩 我很关心
But the boy, he troubles my conscience.
如果Barca执行了我的命令 做出了如此行为...
If Barca exceeded my orders and laid hand to such an act...
不 他没有杀那个男孩
No, he didn't kill the boy.
或许 你只是迎合我才这么说的
Perhaps you only tell me what I wish to hear.
不 不 不是的
No, no, no.
是他告诉我的
He told me so himself.
他发誓 他没有伤害那个孩子
He swore he'd never harm a child.
哦 那这样 就不必受到良心谴责了
Well this gives reason to put conscience to rest.
他知道了 会很高兴的
He'll be so pleased to know it.
我们还要隐瞒他一段时间
We'll keep it from him yet a while.
我不想用如此肮脏的想法
I do not wish to taint the celebration
玷污此次庆典
with such dark thoughts.
是 主人
Yes, Dominus.
谢谢你的坦诚以待 Pietros
Thank you for your honesty, Pietros.
那男人的本性已暴露无疑
The true nature of the man is revealed.
我真想不到他会这样
I would not have thought it of him.
先让Barca快活一会吧
Let Barca hoist his cup a while.
当他的理智被酒灌晕的时候
When his wits are damp with wine
我再好好奖励他的"忠诚"
then I will see him rewarded for his loyalty.
是 主人
Dominus.
你浑身酒味
You smell of wine.
我是来庆祝的 还带了酒
I bring cups, full of celebration.
我敬佩你的胜利
I honor your victory.
正祷告着呢
With prayer.
多亏了你 我才有可能和妻子团聚
Your instruction made possible reunion with my wife.
万分感激 敬您一杯
I would raise cups in gratitude.
你的心意我领了
The sentiment is well received.
但我已经多年不沾酒了
But wine has not passed my lips for many years.
是因为信仰吗?
Your gods forbid it?
不是
No.
是原则问题
It is a matter of discipline.
Sura也常这样警告我
Sura always cautioned toward the same.
贤惠的女人
A wise woman.
与丈夫相隔万里
Far beyond the station of her husband.
如果我的生命没有她的话...
If she had not come into my life...
现在不是要回来了嘛
and now she returns.
真是神明保佑啊
The gods have truly blessed you.
Sura也会这么说的
Sura would say the same.
你呢?
And you?
我总是跟神对着干
The gods and I do not tread common ground.
虽然她多次劝我
Although she made effort many times
不要大逆不道
to place us at even footing.
好个通情达理的贤惠女人
Wise and understanding.
爱一个人 就爱他的全部...
To love a man despite his shortcomings...
她是我活下去的唯一理由
She is the only reason my heart beats within my chest.
尘世间还能有这样的爱...
To find love such as this...
几辈子修来的福分啊
A rare and fortunate thing.
你很清楚啊?
You speak from knowledge?
我也有妻室
A wife of my own.
她的关怀 一直让我念念不忘
The thought of her ever upon my mind.
她还活着吗?
Does she live?
活在我记忆中
In memory.
真想见她一面啊
I would have desired to meet her.
还要告诉她 你是个好丈夫
And tell her of her husband's worth.
抱歉打断你的祷告
Apologies for disturbing your prayers.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
于胜利而言 我不能喝这杯酒
I cannot drink to victory.
但于你的妻子
But to your wife,
还有她要回来的喜悦...
and her joyous return...
这会就别提什么原则了
Discipline gives way to the moment.
我们敬您
You honor us.
哇哦 主人都说什么了?
Wow, what did the Dominus require?
没什么重要的...
Nothing of import...
你吻我别有用心吧
You kiss with purpose.
是自由之念啊...
For the thought of freedom...
能容我 插句话吗
A word, if I may.
没带钱来的话 就闭嘴滚开
Fuck your words, unless coupled with coin.
那还真来对了
The very matter I came to discuss.
我从Marcellus那儿借到了一大笔钱
I've secured a sizeable loan from good Marcellus,
足够顶上你的赌金
to cover your winnings.
不过利息要得有点离谱...
The terms of interest were outrageous...
给我看看
Give it here.
等今早 Marcellus凑齐了 就会带来的
Marcellus will bring it when he collects his whore, in the morning.
什么都没有 你还来打扰老子快活?
You interrupt my cock with empty hands?
还有别的消息
And intelligence.
Batiatus知道你渴望自由
Batiatus knows of your desire for freedom,
要趁热打铁 尽早说啊
and makes noise for discussing terms.
你在竞技场上的表现 让人印象深刻
Your skills, while impressive in the arena,
但在谈判这事上 您还差点哪
lack a certain gentle touch in the art of negotiation.
但我能和Batiatus通融一下 给你的自由
I can offer to bargain a better price from Batiatus
争取个好价钱
for your release.
我欠你的钱 差不多一半就够了
Half the difference to be subtracted from my debt to you.
Batiatus 还是挺通情达理的
Batiatus is in agreeable spirits.
我们快去吧...
If we move with haste...
去啊
Go.
走吧 最后一次叫他主人
Let's go and call him Dominus, for the final time.
我听说 你想要离开这儿
I hear whispers you seek freedom.
这次讨论 Ashur代表我发言
Ashur represents me in the discussion.
讨论?
Discussion?
没什么好说的了
There's none to be had in the matter.
从你胆敢违背我的那刻起...
The bond between master and slave has already been dissolved...
你我就已经不是主人和奴隶的关系了
the moment you disobeyed me.
违背?
Disobeyed?
Ovidius的儿子还活着
The son of Ovidius lives.
不可能啊
Impossible.
行政官正十万火急地找他呢
The Magistrate rides to retrieve him.
只要那小子还活着
Yet breathing, small fingers trembling
终究会找到我的头上
to reveal the beast that took away his family.
不可能
This cannot be.
我亲手扼住他的咽喉
My hands upon his throat,
我看着他死的
I felt the life flee from his body.
你的小情人可不是这么说的
Your lover spoke otherwise.
Pietros吗?
Pietros?
你告诉他男孩还活着
You told him the boy lives.
对吗?
Did you not?
是的
I did.
那是为了安抚他
But only to calm him.
如果他知道 孩子是我杀的...
If he knew the child's blood stained my hands...
那你是骗他的?
So you lied to him?
也许现在 他在骗您呢
Or he lies to you now.
不论怎样 我已经不相信你了
Either way, we've a serious issue of trust.
主人 听我解...
Dominus, let me expl...
杀了他!
well, stop him!
现在你自由了
Now you're free.
Barca赎回了自由
Barca purchased his freedom.
我们送他出门
We wished him well
祝他一路好走
and escorted him through the gates of the villa.
就这么说 明白了吗?
Do you understand?
是 主人
Yes, Domina.
你真记住了?
Do you understand?
是!
Yes!
开门啊
Open up.
奶奶的!
Juno's cunt!
又是谁啊?!
What now?!
行政官驾到
Make way for the Magistrate.
糟了!?
Fuck!?
快把窗帘拉上!
Close the curtains!
Santos 把血迹清理干净
Santos clean the blood up in there,
快弄干净!
get it cleaned up!
让开!
Make way!
Batiatus出来!
Batiatus!
行政官啊
Magistrate.
您来得真不巧啊
You call at unexpected hour.
我可没时间跟你耗
Drawn by matters that will not wait for dawn.
怎么又见血了?
What new offense is this?
哦 没什么
Ah, nothing.
一个不听话的奴隶 教训了几下
A disobedient slave, freshly corrected.
今天要受皮肉之苦的 可不止他一个
Not the only wretch deserving of blood this night.
我去见Ovidius的儿子 刚回来
I have just now returned from the promised reunion with Ovidius' son,
我有话要问你的人
and would have words with a man seen in your house.
您说的是哪个人?
Which man do you speak of?
那个骗了我的信使
The messenger that filled my heart with false hope.
信使?
Messenger?
根本没人见过Ovidius的儿子
Ovidius' child was not seen on any road.
回到城里
Returning to the city,
在我堂弟家的废墟里
we had news that his body was discovered
才找到孩子的尸体
among the ashes of my cousin's villa.
是信使撒了谎...
The messenger lied...
我真不该随便
I will have knowledge of the reason,
听信一个傻瓜的谎话
along with the fool's tongue.
我一定不惜代价 把这个混蛋抓来
Every effort will be exhausted until the villain is discovered.
给你钱
Coin.
谢你的
Paired with gratitude.
信使让你达成心愿了 对不?
The messenger had the desired effect, then?
我终于安心了
My concerns have been laid to rest,
不用怕被Barca拖死 也不用还他钱了
sharing grave with Barca and his thirst for winnings.
行政官应该不会
There's no chance the Magistrate
查到消息的来源吧?
will deduce the source of this message?
只要阎王不开口 没人知道的
Not unless Hades speaks of it from the underworld.
嗯
Um.
信使已经死了
The messenger has been put to grass.
你要是敢再提起这事
And you will follow,
哪怕一个字 下一个死的就是你
if a word of this transaction parts your lips again.
我屎都吐出来了
I shit myself.
Ashur啊?
Ashur?
Ashur啊
Ashur.
哦 小Pietros!
Young Pietros!
什么风把你吹来了?
How does the day find you?
我担心了整个晚上
As the night, filled with worry.
Barca一直没回来
Barca never returned.
他不会回来了
Nor will he.
他已经自由啦
He has his freedom.
自由?
Freedom?
可不
Yes.
他已经从主人那儿赎身了
Purchased from our Dominus.
他走的时候 我追都追不上呢
I could barely keep pace as we saw him to the gates.
他要带我一起的啊
He was to take me with him.
你们俩的自由 价钱可不低啊
The price of freedom was too steep for the both of you.
但别担心啦
But do not worry.
Barca一定还能找到一个 比你更嫩的美男的
I'm sure Barca will find another tight hole to sit on his cock.
还不用花钱呢
One he doesn't have to pay for.
我头还晕着呢
Jupiter's cock, my head.
恶心得我都站不起来了
I can barely stand for want of vomit.
你不是唯一一个
You're in large company.
那种情况 谁能把持住啊
No one in condition to halt a man of purpose.
要的就是这效果
Such by design.
平常 Doctores可是太阳没升起来 就开始挥鞭子了
Doctores usually up before the sun, whip in hand.
他还会起来吗
Will he ever rise again?
当然
He will.
可那是几个时辰之后的事了
But not for many hours.
哦 那你的把握就更大了
Oh, your chances improve, then.
那是必然的
To the point of certainty.
不会这么顺利的
Nothing is ever so.
就算你逃出门去
Look even if you ride beyond the gates,
守卫也会紧追不放
the guards will pursue.
他们不会这样做的
They will be commanded against such action.
你还指望他们听你的?
You actually expect them to obey you?
不是
No.
我只希望他们能听主人的话...
I expect them to obey their master...
他妈的给我把剑放下!
Drop your fucking swords!
马上!
Do it!
等到了山阴 我就会放了他
I will release him when we are in the cover of the mountains.
斯巴达克斯!
Spartacus!
你妻子的车快到了!
Your wife's cart appears upon the road!
我跟你一起去!
I'll be with you presently!
最后一次提醒你 慎重考虑啊
I urge you to reconsider one last time.
Sura一定要自由
Sura will be free.
今生 或是来世
In this life, or the one after,
依偎在她的丈夫身边...
with her husband by her side.
愿神明保佑你们能重回色雷斯
May the gods see you both upon the plains of Thrace.
池子现在干净了
The pool is clear.
就像没发生过一样
As if it never happened.
全是误会 令人悔之不及
A regrettable misunderstanding.
直到死 他都是忠诚的
The man was yet loyal.
他渴望自由啊
He wished for his freedom.
这本身就是对我们的背叛
A betrayal in itself.
来吧
Come.
找点乐子去
To happier thoughts.
那个色雷斯人的老婆到了
The Thracian's wife approaches.
他不得高兴坏了?
How is that cause for cheer?
她的到来 只会让他想起过去的生活
Her arrival will only remind him of his old life,
和行尸走肉般的生活
and the ways of an animal.
你怎么就不明白呢?
Why can't you see that?
我们的希望和命运 已经和斯巴达克斯拴在一起了
Our hopes and fortunes are tied to Spartacus.
我承诺让他和妻子团聚
I made a promise to reunite him with his wife.
为了让他死心塌地 我不能食言
In honor of the man, I will keep my word.
来的路上... 不知从哪冒出来一群人...
They came out of nowhere... on the road...
他们... 他们袭击了我们
they attacked... they attacked on the road.
我在这儿呢
I'm here.
我没有食言
My word is kept.
他们团聚了
They're reunited.